<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>UNC MBB TRIVIA</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on UNC MBB TRIVIA</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Average points difference through first N games</title>
      <link>/post/points-difference-season-average/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/points-difference-season-average/</guid>
      <description>Time flies, and the Tar Heels played the season’s first 5 games already. And loosely speaking, they’ve played well so far (knocking on woods), to the eyes of just another casual fan here!
I’m not going to say anything about this season’s fate based on the results of the season’s first 5 games, but still I was curious how well this season compares to other seasons at this point. There could be many different ways to do just that, but I thought looking at each season’s running average of points difference after each regular season game might be interesting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5th year players</title>
      <link>/post/5th-year-players/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/5th-year-players/</guid>
      <description>As I mentioned it in an earlier post, I’ve been wanting to add each season’s players info to my data source. Although it needs more cleaning still, I finally got around to it and got to play with the players data a bit lately.
As part of cleaning the players data, I needed to make sure that for most players, their college careers lasted at most for four years. At one end of the extreme sit those one-and-done players (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Season’s first game</title>
      <link>/post/season-s-first-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/season-s-first-game/</guid>
      <description>UNC MBB team had its first official exhibition game of the 2017-18 season this past week against Barton college. It was the first official exhibition, because there was a scrimmage (unofficial exhibition?) with Memphis team about a week before UNC MBB faced Baron college.
The team’s first official regular season game is in less than 2 weeks against Northern Iowa, and just like they won the unofficial games (with questionable performance) so far, I’d expect the team to start the season with a W.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Season win percentage</title>
      <link>/post/season-win-percentage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/season-win-percentage/</guid>
      <description>This past week, I was in a presentation training, and all the participants had to select a topic on the last day of training to give a (perfect) 15-min presentation. You know, after learning all the essential presentation skills, it was time to apply those fancy skills to work!
I decided to talk about UNC MBB and its great stories behind each of the 3 championship seasons during Williams-era. I made a 5-page deck using Rmd-driven slidy presentation, and I am planning to post it here either in its raw form or after some adjustment using xaringan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Losing Series</title>
      <link>/post/losing-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/losing-series/</guid>
      <description>In my first uncmbbtrivia post last week, I looked at perfect winning series of UNC MBB team, particularly looking for those schools that the team has never lost to since 1949-50 season (minimum of 10 games). Again, say hello to: Citadel, Rutgers, Stanford, and Tulane :)
This week, I look at the opposite end of the series history. Are there any schools that the UNC MBB team kept losing to? I know we haven’t been playing particularly well against Duke lately, so at least I knew depending on how far back I go that there will be some schools that we have losing series against.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Best 4 Year Span</title>
      <link>/post/best-4-year-span/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/best-4-year-span/</guid>
      <description>In my first uncmbbtrivia post last week, I looked at some winning series of UNC MBB team, particularly those schools that the team has never lost to since 1949-50 season (minimum of 10 games). Say hello to: Citadel, Rutgers, Stanford, and Tulane :)
Before writing about the other end of the spectrum in series history, I started reading the 2009 champion season book, “One Fantastic Ride: The Inside Story of Carolina Basketball’s 2009 Championship Season” and posted about it on twitter: “Re-reading my fav 4 seasons of all time in @UNC_Basketball (so far) while waiting on the latest by the great @jadamlucas #uncmbbtrivia”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World!</title>
      <link>/post/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to UNC MBB TRIVIA! Just another casual fan here to talk about UNC Men’s Basketball trivia time to time for all Tar Heels fans to enjoy. Stay tuned!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Winning Series</title>
      <link>/post/winning-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/winning-series/</guid>
      <description>Here it is, the very first trivia! Frankly I was initially curious which schools have winning series against UNC and found out which (and here’s the link to that post), but to start off things on a positive note :) I’m posting which schools have never won against UNC since 1949-50 season while having played UNC at least 10 times.
There they are: Citadel, Rutgers, Stanford, and Tulane! Two of these teams are on UNC’s schedule for upcoming 2017-2018 season, so it’ll be interesting to see if UNC can keep the winning streak.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>